<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the funerall of Mrs. Alice Bray, wife to Francis Bray of Farthingo, neere Brackley in the county of Northampton, Gent. Vpon Psalme 37. and vers. 37. March the 2. 1645. / By W.I. minister there.</title>
            <author>W. I.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E345_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200985</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861584</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861584</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113722</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87265)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113722)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 56:E345[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the funerall of Mrs. Alice Bray, wife to Francis Bray of Farthingo, neere Brackley in the county of Northampton, Gent. Vpon Psalme 37. and vers. 37. March the 2. 1645. / By W.I. minister there.</title>
                  <author>W. I.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Matthew Walbancke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 20th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XXXVII, 37 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113722:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113722:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the FVNERALL OF M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>. ALICE BRAY, wife to FRANCIS BRAY of <hi>Farthingo,</hi> neere <hi>Brackley</hi> in the County of <hi>Northampton,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>Vpon PSALME 37. and verſ. 37. <hi>March</hi> the 2. 1645.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. I.</hi> Miniſter there.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Marke the perfect man, and behold the upright, for the end of that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n is peace.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for MATHEW WALBANCKE, 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:113722:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113722:2"/>
            <head>A FVNERALL SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 37. ver. 37.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright, for the end of that man is peace.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He princely Prophet in this Pſalme perſwadeth to patience, truſt and confidence in God. Theſe duties he enforceth by ſundry forcible Arguments and Reaſons. Theſe Arguments and Reaſons are taken from the different eſtate of the godly and the wicked: And this eſtate of theirs is conſidered either in their life or in their death; in each whereof the difference is very great.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In their life, although the wicked for a time ſeeme to flouriſh, yet they ſhall ſoone be cut downe like the graſſe, and wither as the green herbe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. But on the other ſide, the godly man who truſteth in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113722:3"/>the Lord and doth good, who delights himſelfe in the Lord, commits his way unto the Lord, &amp;c. hee ſhall dwell in the Land, &amp;c. and the Lord ſhall give him the deſires of his heart, &amp;c. Yea, he ſhall bring forth his righteouſneſſe as the light, and his judgement as the noone day, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3, 4, 5. &amp;c. Againe, another diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is, that evill doers ſhall be cut off, but thoſe that wait upon the Lord, <hi>i. e.</hi> reſt in him, and wait pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently for him, they ſhall inherit the earth, and that in a ſhort time, yet a little while, &amp;c. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7, 8, 9, 10, &amp;c. ſuch ſhall be the ſucceſſe both of the one and of the other.</p>
            <p>Moreover another difference is in the carriage and behaviour of the wicked towards the godly, that though the wicked out of envy and malice, plot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the juſt, and gnaſh upon him with his teeth, yet the Lord ſhall laugh at him, &amp;c. yea, though the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked draw out the Sword, and bend their Bow to caſt downe the poore and needy, and to ſlay ſuch as be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, yet their ſword ſhall enter into their owne heart, &amp;c. <hi>verſ.</hi> 12, 13, 14, 15.</p>
            <p>So for their outward eſtate, the wicked may abound in wealth, and the godly live in want, yet a little that a righteous man hath, is better then the riches of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wicked, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. &amp;c. many like differences you may obſerve between them in their outward eſtate, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he verſes enſuing: And alſo in their inward eſtate, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he godly man it is ſaid, The Law of his God is in his heart, &amp;c. But contrarily, the wicked man bearing malice in his heart, hee watcheth the righteous, and ſeeketh to ſlay him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 31, 32. &amp;c. Theſe and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more like differences between the godly and the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113722:3"/>wicked, you may obſerve in the former paſſages of this Pſalme, whereby they differ in the whole courſe of their life.</p>
            <p>But the maine difference between them, whereof the Holy Ghoſt would have us take more ſpeciall no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, is at the end of their life, or at their death; this he would have us more ſeriouſly to conſider, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Mark,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the perfect man, and behold the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, for the end of that man is peace.</hi> But on the other ſide, the tranſgreſſors ſhall be deſtroyed together, the end of the wicked ſhall be cut off, <hi>verſ.</hi> 38.</p>
            <p>Thus as their eſtate is different in the whole courſe and progreſſe of their life, ſo alſo eſpecially at the end of their life, in death; the difference is very great, for the end of the godly and upright, is peace; but the end of the wicked is deſtruction, the tranſgreſſors ſhall be deſtroyed together, the end of the wicked ſhall be cut off, <hi>verſ.</hi> 38.</p>
            <p>I ſhall at this time ſpeake unto you onely of the end of the godly, and of their bleſſed eſtate in death, for the end of ſuch is peace: The end of that man, man put for mankinde, man or woman, of either ſex, or age, young or old, or outward condition, rich or poore, the end of that man (or woman) is peace; and this the Prophet would have us carefully conſider; and therefore, <hi>Mark</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the perfect man, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the upright.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have here a double precept, with a reaſon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing the ſame. 1. The Precept, in theſe words, <hi>Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright.</hi> 2. The Reaſon, in theſe, <hi>for the end of that man, &amp;c.</hi> 1. The Precept, as I ſaid, is double, conſiſting of two bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113722:4"/>yet both expreſſing the ſame thing, <hi>Mark the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man, and behold, &amp;c.</hi> doubled to note (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) both the neceſſity, as alſo the excellencie of the duty, worthy our ſerious obſervation.</p>
            <p>And in each we may obſerve the act and the object: 1. In the firſt, the act is <hi>Mark.</hi> 2. The object or the perſon to be marked and obſerved, is, <hi>the perfect man:</hi> So alſo in the ſecond, 1. The act is <hi>behold,</hi> 2. The object is, the upright, <hi>Behold the upright.</hi> I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to explane each of theſe particulars, and then proceed to inſtruction. 1. In the firſt precept, the act is Mark, <hi>Mark,</hi> ſaith he, &amp;c. Mark, that is conſider diligently, take a ſerious view of him, look upon him wiſhly, and with ſpeciall obſervation, ſo much the word implyeth. 2. The object or perſon thus to be marked, &amp;c. is the perfect man or woman, man for mankinde, as I ſaid, mark the perfect man or woman.</p>
            <p>You will ſay, is there any ſuch man or woman? who can bee juſtly called perfect? who can ſay my heart is cleane, I am pure from my ſinne? who dare aſſume to himſelfe the title of perfection, ſeeing ſo ſanctified a veſſell as <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe, ſaith of himſelfe, that he had not already attained, either were already perfect? <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, perfection in ſome ſenſe cannot be deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto a Chriſtian, for then in vaine were this and all ſuch like precepts to obſerve it, or exhortations to endeavour it, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. &amp;c. A Chriſtian man or woman may in ſome reſpects be called perfect, or elſe how ſhould we mark the perfect man, if there were none ſuch? or why ſhould we be exhorted to goe on to perfection, if perfection could not be attained.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:113722:4"/>
            <p>To reſolve this doubt therefore more clearely and fully, it is neceſſary that we diſtinguiſh of perfection, and thereby make enquiry into the ſeverall kindes thereof, and thence ſee in what ſenſe a man may bee called perfect: Know we therefore that a Chriſtian man or woman may rightly be ſaid to be perfect ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry wayes; for inſtance,</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Chriſtian may be perfect in reſpect of accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, though not in reſpect of operation; namely, in reſpect of Gods acceptance, who of his infinite goodneſſe, accepts the will for the deed; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as in caſe of liberality to the poore, ſo in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther duty, whether of piety to God, or charity to man: If there be firſt a willing mind, it is accepted according to that a man hath, &amp;c. ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. If a man or woman have a willing minde, joyned with a readineſſe of endeavour unto holy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and duties, it is accepted with God as perfect o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience: Thus is he perfect in reſpect of accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is, of Gods acceptance, though not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of operation, his owne beſt workes deſerving no ſuch thing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Chriſtian man or woman may be ſaid to bee perfect comparatively, though not poſitively or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely; comparatively, in reſpect of others, though not poſitively or abſolutely in himſelfe: For exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, if a Chriſtian that devotes himſelfe to ſerve God in ſincerity, be compared with wicked, carnall, and worldly-minded men, who ſerve him not, he is perfect in compariſon of them.</p>
            <p>So he or ſhe that makes conſcience of their wayes, though they have many failings, weakneſſes, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113722:5"/>therein, and ſo not poſitively and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely perfect in themſelves; yet are they perfect in compariſon of others that make no conſcience of their courſes, but follow their owne corrupt and vile affections, and ſeek not the power of godlineſſe, thus is he perfect comparatively, though not poſitively and abſolutely.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Chriſtian man or woman may be perfect E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelically, though not legally, that is, after ſuch ſort as the Goſpel accepts, although not as the Law enjoynes; for perfection of the Law, is, when a man loves God and his Neighbour, according to the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Law, namely, loveth God with all the heart, might, mind and ſtrength, and his neighbour as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; this perfection of love is found in no man in this mortall condition.</p>
            <p>But 2. perfection of the Goſpel is that endeavour of obedience, which God accepts in Chriſt, at the hands of his children; which if it be in truth, ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſingleneſſe of heart, it is accepted: Thus is he or ſhe a perfect man or woman, that deſires and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours after perfection, though in act they attaine it not: And ſo is the Apoſtle to be underſtood in that place before named, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12. not as though I have already attained, or were already perfect, <hi>i.e.</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the perfection which the Law requireth.</p>
            <p>And yet afterward hee ſpeaketh of himſelfe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as being perfect, <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. <hi>Let us therefore,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as many as be perfect, be thus minded;</hi> that is, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as be perfect according to the Goſpel, namely, ſo as the Goſpel accepts perfection, that is, ſo it be in truth, ſincerity, and ſingleneſſe of heart: This ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113722:5"/>is the perfection of a Chriſtian: And ſo were. <hi>Noah, Abraham, Iob, Zachary,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> perfect in their Generations, that is, ſincere in the ſight of God both in heart and life.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A Chriſtian man or woman may be perfect in reſpect of parts, though not in reſpect of degrees: Perfection in parts, is when he hath all the parts of perfection, though in a weake meaſure: Perfection in degrees, is when he hath a full meaſure of Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in every part: For example, a child new borne is a perfect man in reſpect of his parts, becauſe he hath all the parts and members of a man; but hee is not perfect in degree, till every part grow up to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>So the child of God when he is new borne, by his ſecond birth or regeneration (whereof mention is made, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.3, 5.) is perfect in reſpect of parts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath all the parts of perfection, is renewed and changed in every part, though in a weake mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and therefore the Apoſtle calls it a being ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified wholly, and a preſerving blameleſſe of the whole ſpirit ſoule and body, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.23. that is in all parts of ſoule and body, but yet he is not perfect in degrees, <hi>i.e.</hi> in that full meaſure and degree which the Law requireth in every part.</p>
            <p>Thus it is ſaid of <hi>Aſa,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.17. that the heart of <hi>Aſa</hi> was perfect all his dayes, and yet in the ſame place it is ſaid, the high places were not taken away out of Iſrael, thoſe idolatrous places were not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved by him; yea, he failed in other things alſo, for it is ſaid, <hi>chap.</hi> 16.12. that in his diſeaſe be ſought not to the Lord, but to the Phyſitians: So then <hi>Aſa</hi> had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113722:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113722:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:113722:7"/>perfection in parts, he had a perſect heart, and ſo alſo perfection in ſome meaſure in all parts, but he attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to perfection in degrees, be had not a ſull mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and degree of perfection in all parts, for he failed in the things before-named; he had his imperfection thorow the weakneſſe of ſanctification, which is not perfectly attained to in this life.</p>
            <p>By all which it appeareth, that perfection cannot be denyed, but that a Chriſtian man or woman may attaine it, for ſo here you ſee ſuch a one called a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man, <hi>Mark the perfect man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perfect in reſpect of Gods acceptation, though not in reſpect of his own workes or opperation, God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting his will more then deeds. 2. Perfect compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively, though not poſitively or abſolutely, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of others not yet converted or ſanctified, though not poſitively and abſolutely in himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Perfect Evangelically, though not legally, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly as the Goſpel accepts, though not as the Law enjoynes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Perfect in reſpect of parts, though not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of degrees; having all the parts of perfection, though not a full meaſure of perfection in every de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; and this is the perfect man we are here to mark, and ſo you have the ſenſe of the firſt Precept, <hi>Marke the perfect man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I may ſay of the ſecond, as our Saviour did of the ſecond Table of the Law, <hi>the ſecond is like unto it;</hi> for ſo indeed it is; and but, a further deſcription of the godly, who as in the former is called perfect, ſo in this latter, upright, <hi>and behold the upright.</hi> Here is alſo both the act and the object: 1. the Act is <hi>behold,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:113722:7"/>2. The Object or perſon is <hi>the upright;</hi> both theſe are in a manner the ſame with the former, and therefore I ſhall more briefly inſiſt thereon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Act is, <hi>behold,</hi> that is, take a ſerious view, look diligently, and with conſideration, conſider well, 2. <hi>The upright,</hi> that's the object: And this up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe is the ſecond property, whereby the godly man is here deſcribed, which is more fully enlarged <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.11. <hi>upright in heart;</hi> that is, ſound and ſincere without guile, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. And this is, when the heart is ſet right towards God in doing all duties of piety and charity towards God and men, truly aiming at the pleaſing of God, and not at by-reſpects: this is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of heart, called truth in the inward parts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.6. thou loveſt truth in the inward parts.</p>
            <p>And although no man is indeed upright, without ſome crookedneſſe and declining from the ſtraight rule; yet becauſe here is, firſt a drawing neere, and endeavour after full perfection. Secondly, a comparative rightneſſe, in reſpect of the unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, whoſe courſe is wholly crooked. Thirdly, the acceptance of a mercifull Father, therefore they are called upright. And thus you have the meaning of both Precepts, both in the act and object, <hi>Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us ſee what may be obſerved from hence for our further inſtruction: And firſt of all, it is worthy our enquiry, why we are ſo earneſtly exhorted here, and that by a double precept, to mark the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man, and behold the upright; that is, to take ſuch a ſerious view of them, to look ſo wiſhly upon them, and with conſideration; ſurely, there is weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113722:8"/>reaſons why we ſhould do ſo, or elſe it would never be ſo earneſtly preſſed upon us.</p>
            <p>And indeed many reaſons might be rendred, and time would faile to enlarge them; I will only pitch upon one, which I take to be moſt principall, and that is this, <hi>Marke the perfect man, and behold the upright;</hi> namely, for your imitation, mark and behold them, that you may imitate and follow them in their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, upright, and religious converſation, and this will direct us to this duty comprized in this Doctrine, namely,</p>
            <p>That we are thus to honour the Saints living and dead, eminent in gracious practice, by following their holy examples. To this end therefore I ſay, chiefly, <hi>Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright,</hi> that we may make choice of them for our patternes, and follow their good examples.</p>
            <p>To this end, St. <hi>Iames</hi> thus exhorteth, <hi>chap.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Take my brethren the Prophets for an example of ſuffering affliction and of patience:</hi> And S. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo claimes to himſelfe this honour, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Brethren be followers together of me, and mark them which walk ſo:</hi> Mark them, why ſo? as yee have us for an enſample, ſaith hee; namely, that you may follow our example: And ſo alſo he chargeth Gods people, to afford the like to their Paſtors, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7. Remember them which have the rule over you, &amp;c. whoſe Faith follow, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the end of their converſation. Mark, and behold that ye may follow their faith, &amp;c. The Lord hath dealt very mercifully with us, as in many other things, ſo herein eſpecially, in providing us all helpes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for our ſalvation. Two ſenſes there are of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113722:8"/>learning, ſight and hearing, they are neither of them without their meanes of inſtruction.</p>
            <p>As to our hearing hee hath furniſhed us with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors according to his heart, which ſhall feed us with knowledge and underſtanding <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.15 and hath given us in our congregations, as formerly to the Jewes in the wilderneſſe, the voyce of cryers, <hi>Prepare the way of the Lord, Matth.</hi> 3.3. to whom we ought to attend and hearken what the Lord God will ſay.</p>
            <p>So to our ſight, he hath not onely laid open the Booke of Scriptures, but alſo the great Booke of his creatures, wherein the rudeſt may reade his power and wiſdome, in plain characters written, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſhewes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. the inviſible things of him from the Creation of the world are clearely ſeen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing underſtood by the things that are made, even his eternall power, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Yea, moreover to both theſe, he hath ſet before us the practice of his Saints, whoſe converſation we may ſee, and whom we are here called upon to mark and behold, by their perfection and uprightreſſe, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing out unto us the way that leadeth unto life, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in providing, not onely the honour of his eminent Saints, but alſo our inſtruction and encouragement to ſanctity, perfection, uprightneſſe, and integrity, for theſe reaſons eſpecially.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Knowing how naturally we are addicted to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and how examples move more then words, as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaid, <hi>Validior ect operis quam eris vox,</hi> the voice of workes is of more force then of words. In this he would not be wanting unto us, that if we will needs be imitating, we may have ſuch patternes as ſhall not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113722:9"/>miſlead us into errour; but contrarily, ſuch as ſhall lead us on to perfection and uprightneſſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to this end we muſt <hi>mark the perfect man, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the upright,</hi> and ſo honour them by following their holy examples.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides, leſt any ſhould be diſcouraged with the opinion of inſuperable difficulty in the practice of the duties ſo to be imitated; he hath ſampled us with men of our owne mould, ſubject to like infirmities, that in the hardeſt and harſheſt of Chriſtian offices, have gone before us; inſomuch that the duty cannot be named ſo hard or harſh to fleſh and blood, wherein ſome of his Saints have not gone before us.</p>
            <p>That, I think, may well be numbred amongſt the moſt hard and difficult propoſed by our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.38. Namely, to take up our croſſe and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after him: And can we name the croſſe that ſome of the Saints have not comfortably endured? It is hard you will ſay to part with goods, yet there were ſome that ſuffered that ſpoile with joy, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. It is hard to exchange hopes of advancement and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment for rebukes; yet is this choſen willingly by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and counted honourable, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.26. eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the reproach of Chriſts greater riches then the treaſures in <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were much, yea too much for many, to leave Country and Kindred and fathers houſe, yet did not <hi>Abraham</hi> ſo? <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.1. &amp;c. Hardeſt of all were it to leave life, (ſith skin for skin, yea all that a man hath will he give for his life, <hi>Job</hi> 2.4.) eſpecially to leave it by violent torments; yet what death can we think of, ſo full of ſhame or torture, but hath bin endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113722:9"/>by the Saints of God, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.37. &amp;c. they were ſtoned, they were ſawne aſunder, &amp;c. ſo fatherly hath the Lord provided for our benefit, in providing this honour for his Saints, whom we are to mark and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that we may imitate and follow their godly and religious examples whether in doing or ſuffering.</p>
            <p>This honor therefore we willingly afford the Saints, to make them our preſidents and patternes in holy practice, or if there be any other of due praiſe and commemoration of their vertues warranted by that ſaying of our Saviour touching that fact of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, powring ointment on his body for his buriall, Verily, ſaith hee, whereſoever this Goſpel ſhall bee preached in the whole world, there alſo ſhall this that this woman hath done, be told for a memoriall of her, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.12, 13. and ſo alſo the author to the <hi>Hebr. chap.</hi> 11. doth commemorate at large the Faith and other vertues of the Saints, to their perpetuall praiſe and commendation.</p>
            <p>Yet this ſufficeth not our adverſaries the Papiſts, to give this honour to the Saints, but they cenſure us as ſacrilegious, becauſe we give them not Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, namely, the honour of invocation, becauſe we doe not pray unto them, and make them our interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours to God, though <hi>Auguſtine</hi> long ſince delivered it for a rule, <hi>Honorandi ſunt propter imitationem non adorandi propter religionem;</hi> the Saints are to be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for imitation, not worſhipped for Religion; and can they be more diſhonoured by any meanes, then by being made Idols?</p>
            <p>Judge in your ſelves, whether doe more diſhonour them, we by denying them invocation; or Papiſts by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113722:10"/>refuſing imitation, which God hath allowed them; let it therefore ſuffice us to marke and obſerve them for our imitation.</p>
            <p>It is not impertinent here to adde that enquiry, how farre the Saints practice may be our patterne; and how farre their example warrants or binds us to imitation?</p>
            <p>For anſwer whereunto, wee muſt know, that their actions admit this diſtinction: 1. Some of them are noted as ſinfull (for the beſt have not been without their failings) wherein they bewrayed humane frailty, theſe are ſpectacles of naturall infirmity, not exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for like practice; they are written for our cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not for imitation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond ſort were done by vertue of ſpeciall diſpenſation: So <hi>Abraham</hi> attempts to ſlay his ſon, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.10. ſo the Iſraelites rob and ſpoile the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.35, 36. This is no warrant of couſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to any man, for the generall rule bindes us to owe nothing to any man but love, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.8. and it is a mark of the ungodly, to borrow without conſcience of paying againe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.21.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third kind they did by ſpeciall and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary calling; as <hi>Abraham</hi> leaves his countrey for pilgrimage in <hi>Canaan, Gen.</hi> 12.1, &amp;c. as <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> profeſſed a kind of hermitage in the wilderneſſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.1. Is not the popiſh inference pretty from thence? Therefore Pilgrimages are ſatisfactory, Hermitage a ſtate of perfection.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There is a fourth kinde occaſioned by ſpeciall neceſſity of times, or apparance of ſcandall; ſo the primitive Chriſtians had all things common, <hi>Act.</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:113722:10"/>4.32. and <hi>Paul</hi> makes his hands miniſter to his neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.34. Yet there is no footing herein from theſe examples for Anabaptiſticall communitie, nor neceſſity laid on Miniſters to uſe manuall labour, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept where caſes and times are alike to thoſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The laſt ſort of the actions of Saints, which are principally, if not onely, written for our imitation, were their practices which doe accord with the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Law morall, ſuch as thoſe of patience, humility, meekneſſe, obedience, &amp;c. herein is our bond of imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to follow them in the practice of theſe and the like Chriſtian graces and vertues, marke and behold them, herein to imitate them.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Sara</hi> is commended to our womens imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for modeſty and gravity in attire, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3, 4, 5, 6. What ſhould I multiply words in this reſpect? The Apoſtle himſelfe hath ſet us our line, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.6. namely, that we become ſollowers of them and of the Lord: Chriſt is the patterne of patternes, the rule and meaſure of all examples; Take my yoake upon you, and learne of me, ſaith he, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.29. for I am meck and lowly in heart, &amp;c. therefore <hi>Paul</hi> to his precept, <hi>Be yee followers of me,</hi> ſets this limit, <hi>even as I alſo am of Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1.</p>
            <p>In him as the gifts of grace were tranſcendant, ſo their exerciſe ſupereminent; hee erres not that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows Chriſt as his precedent, in any thing wherein he is commanded imitation, nor he that followes the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles or Diſciples of Chriſt, with the limitations before-named, to this and therefore marke and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the perfect and upright, to imitate and follow their holy example in all gracious practices.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:113722:11"/>
            <p>And to encourage herein, conſider the reaſon here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto annexed, <hi>for the end of that man is peace:</hi> In which reaſon is ſet down the different eſtate of the godly and the wicked in the end of their life, and in their death; for whereas the end of the wicked is deſtruction, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 38. the end of the perfect and upright man is peace.</p>
            <p>For the better underſtanding whereof, wee muſt know, that peace is thus tripled by Divines, 1. Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall: 2. Externall: 3. Eternall.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Internall peace is the tranquility of the minde and conſcience in God, ſatisfied in the ſence of his goodneſſe, and is a fruit of Juſtification; for as <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Being juſtified by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> this is that peace which paſſeth all underſtanding, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.7. and of this it is rightly ſaid, no man knoweth it, but he that enjoyeth it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Externall peace is the quiet and concord in our outward eſtate and carriage with men, as betwixt a man and his neighbour, &amp;c. when we keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.3. and this is either domeſticall, or eccleſiaſticall, or politicall.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Domeſticall, or houſhould peace, which ſhews it ſelfe by freedome from bitterneſſe, diſcords or any abſurd peeviſh paſſions in our houſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Ecoleſiaſticall, or Church-peace, which is not onely a reſt from perſecution, but alſo from diſcords within the Church; this peace is a holy amity and heavenly concord in the true members of the myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body, both in conſent and doctrine.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Politicall peace, and that's either private, and ſo it is a reſt from ſuits and quarrels; or publike, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113722:11"/>ſo it is a reſt from warres, and rebellions, and tumults: Theſe be the branches of peace externall.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Peace externall, is the bleſſed reſt of the Saints in Heaven, for at the end of this life they ſhall enter into peace, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.2. where is the moſt perfect tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of order, where wee are ſet out of touch or reach of the Divels wrangling, or any of his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Now, although all theſe kinds of peace may in ſome ſort be applied to the perfect and upright man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; becauſe, if it be poſſible, as much as lyeth in them, they would live peaceably with all men, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.18. yet I take it, that here principally is meant the firſt and the laſt kinde; and ſo the ſence is this, the end of the perfect and upright man or woman, is peace, that is, they have peace of conſcience, peace with God through Jeſus Chriſt, &amp;c. and ſo enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to peace eternall in heaven: So then, here you ſee, as was ſaid, one maine difference between the godly and the wicked in the end of their life; the end of the one is peace, of the other deſtruction: The end of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and upright man is peace, but the tranſgreſſors ſhall bee deſtroyed together, the end of the wicked ſhall be cut off.</p>
            <p>I ſhall onely, and that briefly, ſpeake of the former at this time; namely, the end of the perfect and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, which is peace; peace both internall and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall: 1. Internall of the mind and conſcience in God ſatisfied in the ſenſe of his goodneſſe, and aſſurance of his mercy in Chriſt. The collection is plaine from the Text, that the godly man or woman ſhall make a peaceable end, their mind and conſcience very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113722:12"/>in death; for mark the perfect man, &amp;c. the end of that man is peace.</p>
            <p>It is truly affirmed by the wiſe man, that the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hath hope in his death, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.32. that is, the man juſtified before God by Chriſt, and ſtudying and endeavouring to walk in the wayes of righteouſneſſe in his life, when death commeth, he quietly awaiteth the Lords good leiſure, in aſſured hope of entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a place of reſt, by the merit and death of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This appeares alſo in <hi>Pauls</hi> diſpoſition, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. having a deſire to depart, or to be let looſe, and you may ſee in him the true diſpoſition of a religious man of a perfect and upright man or woman, ſo farre was he from endeavouring to put death out of his minde, as if it were a terrour to think thereon: As that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily, he took comfort in remembring it: So farre was he from fearing, leaſt it ſhould come too ſoone upon him, that he rather deſired it, and the delaying thereof was irkeſome to him: This therefore is an argument, that <hi>Pauls</hi> thoughts reſpectively to death were very comfortable, and his end peace, when as that which man naturally feareth, he deſired with all ſpeed to come unto, having a deſire to depart.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſeen in that good old <hi>Simeon,</hi> who did even in a manner beg of God to be diſmiſſed, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.29. <hi>Lord now letteſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace:</hi> And to aſſure us, that his deſire herein proceeded not from any worldly diſcontent; he ſpeakes of a depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in peace, as an evidence of ſome feeling of peace betwixt God and his ſoule, and giveth his reaſon of it, <hi>for mine eyes have ſeen thy ſalvation:</hi> He had now as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113722:12"/>much ſpirituall comfort and contentment, as in this world could be hoped for, and was therefore now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous (if it might ſtand with Gods good pleaſure) to end his dayes in the midſt of that ſweet peace which he felt in great abundance in his ſoule.</p>
            <p>It was the bleſſing that God promiſed to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 15.15. that he ſhould goe to his fathers in peace, which is to be referd, not only to the reſt which God meant to give him before his death, from all his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer travels, but alſo to the comfortable diſpoſition of his ſoule, at the end of his life, that then he ſhould goe to his fathers in peace: Thus it is plaine that the godly man or woman ſhall make a peaceable end, their mind and conſcience ſhall be very comfortable in death.</p>
            <p>Neither is it thus with the godly, the perfect and upright men and women without cauſe; for 1. it fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſo with them through the aſſurance which they have of reconciliation with God through Jeſus Chriſt: How can this but breed peace and quietneſſe in the mind and conſcience, when I am perſwaded and aſſured in my ſoule and ſpirit, that all cauſe of danger after death is utterly removed, and that God both is and ever will be gracious unto me in his Son Chriſt Jeſus?</p>
            <p>This was the ground of the Apoſtles confidence, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. he knew that ſo ſoone as hee was departed hence, he ſhould be with Chriſt, which is farre bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and therefore he deſired this departure: He that felt himſelfe now in Chriſt, could not but be aſſured that hee ſhould afterwards be with Chriſt, and ſo at peace. To whomſoever God gives Chriſt, he gives all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113722:13"/>things, for all things are in Chriſt; and therefore he that hath Chriſt, hath life, and all things pertaining thereunto, righteouſneſſe, peace, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now if it bee queſtioned, whether the ſervants of God, the perfect and upright, have this aſſurance of their reconciliation, and ſo of peace? I anſwer, it is certaine, that ſooner or later, they all have it in ſome meaſure; for it is ſaid plainly, <hi>They which are Chriſts, have the Spirit of Christ, and if any have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his,</hi> Rom. 8.9. And againe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>This Spirit beareth witneſse with our ſpirit of our adoption, that we are the children of God.</hi> Here is a double teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, Gods Spirit and our ſpirit, and theſe give evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our adoption, and conſequently of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation and peace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This peace proceedeth alſo from the comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble teſtimony of their conſcience, touching their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer care to glorifie God in uprightneſſe of heart and holineſſe of converſation. Hence came <hi>Pauls</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>I have fought a good fight,</hi> ſaith he, and this encouraged him to expect that Crown of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, which the Lord reſerves for all which love his appearing.</p>
            <p>Conſider to this purpoſe the example of <hi>Hezekiah, Iſa.</hi> 38.1. &amp;c. he knew, no doubt, that he muſt dye, but at that time there mentioned, when the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> came unto him from the Lord with this dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meſſage, <hi>Set thy houſe in order, for thou ſhalt dye, and not live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whom would not theſe tydings have ſtrucken to the heart, and what could <hi>Hezekiah</hi> then expect but preſent death? Well then, all things thus threatning
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113722:13"/>his end, the common condition of nature, the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of the preſent ſickneſſe, (being as it is thought, the Plague) and above all, the doome brought from the Lord by the hand of ſuch a Prophet: Where now was the ſtaffe of <hi>Hezakiahs</hi> comfort, but even the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſoule and conſcience, teſtifying unto him the ſincerity and holineſſe of his former courſe? <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member now, O Lord,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. <hi>how I have welked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even ſo alſo could that good old <hi>Simeon,</hi> with a glad ſpirit have beſought the Lord even inſtantly to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe him, if his conſcience had not told him, that all his life paſt had been an intentive waiting for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of <hi>Iſrael, Luk.</hi> 2.25, 26. thus the piety, the purity, the ſincerity of their former courſes hath ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured theſe worthies of the glory to come, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all procured their preſent peace, and the ſame ground of peace hath every perfect and upright man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
            <p>Neither is this ſo, becauſe of any connexion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween work and wages, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if Gods children ſhould build their hopes upon merit or deſerts; for they know, that when they have done what poſſible they can, they are yet unprofitable ſervants, &amp;c. but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they know good workes to be the way to the Kingdome, but not the cauſe of reigning, God hath ordained, that we ſhould walke in them, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10. And they find by the Scripture, that an holy life here is the firſt fruits of a glorious life herefares; and ſo the conſcience of their former courſe is the aſſurer, not the deſerver of their happineſſe; the evidence,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113722:14"/>not the cauſe of their peace. Thus for peace inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall in the minde and conſcience, whereof the godly are partakers, not onely in life, but in death, they ſhall make a peaceable end, their conſcience very comfortable in death; <hi>For mark the perfect man, &amp;c. for the end of that man is peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is alſo equally true touching their peace eternall, for at the end of his life, the perfect or righteous ſhall enter into peace; they ſhall reſt in their beds, &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.2. they ſhall enter into eternall peace and reſt. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> is an evidence to us of the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſtate of all perfect and upright men or women. Now he ſpeaketh confidently, that no ſooner ſhould his ſoule be ſeperated from his body, but it ſhould be by and by with Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. Death ſhould bee but as a door opening unto him, a ſpeedy admittance into the ſociety and preſence of the Lord Jeſus, and ſo at peace.</p>
            <p>And if any ſhould think that <hi>Pauls</hi> caſe herein was ſingular, and that albeit it might be his portion, thus ſpeedily upon his death to be conveyed unto Chriſt; yet it cannot be ſo with every Chriſtian. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle elſewhere puts it out of all queſtion, that herein he did not think himſelfe priviledged as another, as you may obſerve by his owne words, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Per wee know,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>that if our earthly houſe of this Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle were diſſolved, wee have a building of God, an houſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This then by <hi>Pauls</hi> plaine words, is the lot of all true Chriſtians that inſtantly upon the diſſolution of their earthly houſes, which their ſoules here inhabit, they ſhall be admitted into a more excellent kind of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113722:14"/>dwelling, even ſuch a one, wherein being abſent from the body, be preſent with the Lord, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. that is, in peace.</p>
            <p>Needs muſt it be acknowledged, that this place is ſpoken, not of ſome ſpeciall ones, but of all belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, even of all to whom God hath given the earneſt of his Spirit, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. and that is a common favour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon all the Elect, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.22. who hath alſo ſealed us, and given us the earneſt of his Spirit.</p>
            <p>Many other evidences of Scripture might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to this purpoſe: I will onely adde that, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord, from henceforth;</hi> yea, ſaith the Spirit, <hi>that they may reſt from their labours:</hi> Here is a reſt preſently upon death, and what reſt is it, but that peace the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> ſaith, they ſhall enter into, and ſhall reſt in their beds, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus it is cleare, that the end of the perfect and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man is peace, and that both internall and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall: 1. Internall of the minde and conſcience in God, ſatisfied in the ſence of his goodneſſe, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his mercy in Chriſt. 2. Eternall, for at the end of this life, hee ſhall enter into peace eternall in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Now then for application, ſeeing it is ſo, that an endeavoured perfectneſſe and uprightneſſe brings with it in the end of life peace internall, and after this life peace eternall in heaven; <hi>for the end of that man is peace:</hi> Then 1, let us be exhorted to labour for aſſurance of this peace, <hi>That when our earthly houſe of this Tabernacl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall be diſſolved, we may have a building of God, eternall in the heavens,</hi> and to this end,</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113722:15"/>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt labour for aſſurance of reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God by Jeſus Chriſt, for Chriſt is the Prince of peace, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Yea, he is our peace, Epheſ.</hi> 2.14. and therefore onely by him is our peace procured; onely they that are by grace and mercy accepted of God in Chriſt, have their portion in this peace.</p>
            <p>Wouldſt thou then finde inward peace in thy heart and conſcience, to ſtabliſh thee in thy combar againſt the terrours of ſinne and temptation of Satan? thou muſt then ſerve under the Prince or Peace, and becom a ſubject under him, who will poſſeſſe thee with ſuch peace, as ſhall make thee in mourning, and ſuffering perſecution, for righteouſneſſe rejoyce, not onely in the promiſe, but in the poſſeſſion of a preſent happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>In a word, wouldſt thou enjoy peace eternall in Heaven, acquaint thy ſelfe with God, and be at peace, <hi>Job</hi> 22.21. Become a child of the Church, for great ſhall be the peace of her children, <hi>Iſay</hi> 54.13. and that both here and hereafter.</p>
            <p>Humble thy ſelfe, ſue for mercy, labour for increaſe of faith in Chriſt, for onely in him is true peace to be found. Doſt thou perceive God frowning againſt thy ſinne? There is no way for thee, but to get him to behold thee in the face of his anointed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.9. No merits, no workes, no good intentions, no gifts can clear his countenance to make it ſhine upon thee, onely he is well pleaſed in his Chriſt, and with ſuch as he beholdeth in him, and no other: Thus this is the firſt meanes to procure our peace; namely, by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.36.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In the next place wee muſt make conſcience of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113722:15"/>our wayes, going on ſtill to perfection, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. not as though wee had already attained, or were already perfect; but this we ſhould doe, forgeting thoſe things which are behinde, and reaching forth unto thoſe things which are before, we preſſe towards the market for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.13, 14.</p>
            <p>Strive alſo for uprightneſſe, ſincerity and ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart and life, and to keep thy ſelfe unſpotted of the world; this is that which will bring a man peace at the laſt: He that goeth this way, though with much weakneſſe, with many falls, and ſundry imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, yet he cannot miſſe of comfort; for <hi>marke the perfect man, and behold the upright, for the end of that man is peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who ſo then would have peace in death, let him la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to have grace in life. Wouldſt thou end thy dayes happily? Make conſcience to ſpend them ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily; <hi>as many as walk according to this rule, peace be upon them, Gal.</hi> 6.16. the end of ſuch is peace. And ſo much for this time of theſe words.</p>
            <p>Now, I doubt not, beloved, but you will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that this Text may be fitly applyed to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion, and that I may ſay in the words of the <hi>Pſalme, Mark this perfect woman,</hi> conſider diligently, and take ſpeciall obſervation of her, and you ſhall not doubt to call her perfect in the ſence I before named; namely,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Perfect, in reſpect of acceptation, though not in reſpect of operation, God in his infinite goodneſſe and mercy accepting her deſre and endeavour after it, as perfection, though by their beſt workes, neither
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113722:16"/>ſhe, nor any other can attaine it; yet, where there is a willing mind and conſtant endeavour, as was in her, God accepts, as perfect obedience, being graciouſly pleaſed to accept the will for the deed, and full perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, and ſo perfect ſhe was in reſpect of Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Perfect ſhe was alſo comparitively, though not poſitively and abſolutely. In which reſpect wee may ſay of her, as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> of himſelfe, <hi>Iſay</hi> 38.3. <hi>Shee walked before God in truth, and with a perfect heart,</hi> and devoting her ſelfe to ſerve God in ſincerity and ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart: She was perfect in compariſon of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who following their owne corruption, ſought not the power of godlineſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Perfect wee may likewiſe pronounce her to be Evangelically, though not legally: After ſuch ſort as the Goſpel accepts, though not as the Law enjoynes. For though ſhe attained not to that legall perfection: to <hi>love God with all the heart, mind, ſtrength, &amp;c. and her neighbour,</hi> according to the letter of the Law: (which perfection of love, is found in no man in this life) yet perfection of the Goſpel in ſuch an endeavour of obedience, as God accepts in Chriſt, at the hands of his Children, wee doubt not to affirme that ſhee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Perfect finally, wee may conclude her to be, in reſpect of parts, though not in reſpect of degrees, having all the parts of perfection, though not perfect meaſure of degrees in every part; or according to the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 5.23. <hi>Sanctified wholly, the whole ſpirit, ſoule and body preſerved blameleſſe, &amp;c.</hi> no part or power of body or ſoule, but felt the vertue of Gods
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113722:16"/>Spirit purging corruption: yet not perfect in degrees in this full meaſure and degree in every part, which is required.</p>
            <p>And as in this ſenſe, wee may marke her as perfect: So alſo wee may behold her upright. Firſt, ſound and ſincere without guile and: hypocriſie Her heart being ſet right towards God, in doing all duties of Pietie or Charitie, to God or man, truely aiming at the pleaſing of God, and not at any by reſpects; Not, but that ſhe had her failings herein alſo: For there is no man or woman ſo upright, without ſome crooked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and declining from the right rule. Yet becauſe there was in her, Firſt, a drawing neere and endeavour after uprightneſſe. Secondly, a comparitive right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in reſpect of the unregenerate, whoſe courſe is wholly crooked. And thirdly, the acceptance of a mercifull Father; In theſe reſpects, wee may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce her upright, and ſo ſay alſo with the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Behold the upright,</hi> marke and behold her for your imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that you may imitate and follow her, in her perfect upright and religious converſation, even as <hi>Sara</hi> is commended to godly Matrons for imitation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.6. ſo may ſhee, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And for your encouragement mark her end alſo: we doubt not to pronounce that her <hi>end was peace,</hi> &amp; that both externall, internal, &amp; eternal. Firſt, external, being all her life-time of a peaceable condition, of whom we may give like teſtimony, as <hi>Hamor</hi> &amp; <hi>Shechem</hi> did of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> and his retinue, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.21. <hi>Theſe men are peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with us.</hi> So this woman was ever <hi>peaceable with us;</hi> no cauſer of contention, no breaker, but <hi>maker of peace, ſuch ſhall be called the Children of God, Math.</hi> 5.9. noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113722:17"/>of all men, to beare the Image of the <hi>God of peace.</hi> Secondly, internall peace, betweene God and her Conſcience, ſatisfied in the ſenſe of his goodneſſe, whereof ſhee gave many good evidences as my ſelfe can witneſſe, eſpecially thoſe two before named. Firſt, a well-grounded faith, whereby <hi>being juſtified, ſhe had peace with God, &amp;c.</hi> Secondly, a conſtant en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour after perfection and uprightneſſe of heart and life, the end whereof is peace. From which ſo infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble premiſes wee may charitably conclude her eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall peace, in the words of the Prophet, <hi>Iſay</hi> 57.2. that ſhe is now <hi>entred into peace,</hi> even into peace eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall in the Heavens, and there wee leave her at peace and reſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:113722:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
